Well, we've had quite a number of things
happen here since two weeks ago. Two
earthquakes and all kinds of minor
things and uh a heat wave.
But we're not doing as badly as the
Babylonians did at the time of the
writing of the book of Daniel.
One thing about the Old Testament books
that I think most people have not
considered,
the books are attributed to deity,
but no proof of the actual presence of
deity has ever been formally delivered.
They talk about God's will and is very
commonly referred to in the scriptures.
But just under what circumstance this
will expressed itself is usually very
dim. I think the answer is that these
old books are for the most part a record
and an interpretation of experiences.
Most of the Old Testament books and the
scriptures of other peoples are the are
the records of repeating experiences.
If in the course of history in 50
situations the conclusion is always
determined by the integrity of the
circumstance then it is attributed to
deity. In other words, there is proof of
cause and effect. there is proof of
moral value and factor
in the happenings of mankind.
These evidences have been gradually
compiled. For instance, the story that
we have of Jonah and the whale occurs in
several different systems. In fact, in
the Job, of course, in the Jonah, it is
referred to as a great fish. Jesus is
the first one to call it a whale. But
the whale story occurs in Babylon. It
occurs in the far east. It occurs all
over. Always in the remote past.
These stories seem to be therefore a
series of fables like Esop's fables.
Each one with a distinct moral meaning,
a meaning that has continued and been
re-emphasized over periods of thousands
of years.
It is not that a single incidence is
determined. It is that the testimony of
the ages supports certain results as the
results of certain causes.
And as these results of good causes
are nearly always benevolent and the bad
causes nearly always end in tragedy.
This is attributed finally as solid
evidence of the existence of God.
If these different incidents were
haphazard, no pattern, no value obvious,
it might not have followed this pattern
of not read not led to a religious
conclusion. But where certain things
always result in the same conclusions,
it seems reasonable to assume that those
conclusions are the will of something
stronger than the human being. Nature
more powerful than man, God more
powerful than nature. But all with in
behind all of these incidents, an
integrity, a value for value pattern.
And the ancients live building on this
concept for hundreds and thousands of
years put together these fables to
express the evidence of the presence of
a divine power judging all things. Now
the materialist might say that this is
not demonstrable, that it's not true,
that it is all haphazard, that it's all
fancy. But then we look back on Caesar
dead at the foot of Pompy statue.
Alexander dead at the foot of the walls
of Babylon.
Napoleon and Saint Alina. Hitler in the
bunker in Berlin. Mussolini hanging on a
lamp post in Italy. These things all
seem to add up to the fact these men did
not live according to an integrity that
it was acceptable to nature. Now, if
some of one or two of them had been
gloriously successful,
uh we might question it. But where the
same causes and the same circumstances
invariably result in the same
consequences,
we begin to suspect that there is a law
involved. And in the Old Testament, this
law dressed in fable gives us the
wonderful stories of the Old Testament.
They are all cosmic legends or legends
that have been handed down for thousands
of years in new dresses, new
applications, new interpretations, but
always the same essential integrities
and moralities.
It comes out of this that most ancient
people decided that the Lord God or
whoever we may be like to have us behave
ourselves.
When we do not behave ourselves, we
become like small children requiring
chastisement of some kind and always we
get it. Now we have the same problem
here today in the world. We have the
world that prided itself upon its
accomplishments that has apparently
risen above all natural laws that is now
sinking into a morass of corrupted
natural laws. We have done it all wrong
and we're not going to win this way. And
when we go down to the defeat that is
inevitable 5,000 years from now, we will
be evidences of the righteous judgment
of deity.
No one has seen deity. No one's likely
to see him. But his works are obvious.
And there is no other explanation
that man can never defy the laws of
nature without suffering. Now natural
laws are a little different from divine
laws in this factor. The natural laws
are concerned primarily with forms with
bodies with the circumstances of
environment and things of this nature.
Plants and flowers and animals and
creatures of all kinds live according to
their own natures. They have no
individuality such as we have. They live
together. They die together. The whole
groups of them perish together in great
cosmic disasters. But the individual, a
certain higher law takes over. There is
not only the physical laws of nature but
the nor moral laws of ethics. And these
are very very important. The ten
commandments are a good example of this.
presumably given to Moses on Mount Si by
the very hand of God. Actually, those
ten commandments are as old as time. The
most primitive people believed them and
held them to be true because wherever
they were violated, trouble resulted.
Trouble that could not be explained
away. The only way it could be explained
was disobedience.
But but disobedience to what?
disobedience to some kind of an ethical
code that is very difficult to capture
in words but which reaffirms and
reasserts itself wherever conduct of any
kind exists. So out of the mixtures of
these fables legends there comes a sort
of intellectual picture of what the
divine will might be like and what type
of a god there is. Now if we wish to say
that there is no god then we must
attribute all this to the operations of
nature. But nature on the other hand is
not adequate to explain many of these
things. Man's conduct is often in
violation of nature. Sometimes it is
punished by keeping the law of nature
apparently because it is a different
code for the human being. But the fact
remains that wherever we find a code set
up in ancient times like the Justinian
code or the code of Amaradi, we always
find the same essential rules with the
statement that they were divinely
bestowed upon mankind.
This divine bestow was apparently a
series of repetition repetitions of
effects for similar causes that the no
matter how many times we made the same
mistake we had the same punishment for
it. There's no man no of how we got
along doing well time after time we
maybe sacrifice a great deal but we try
very hard and somewhere in the pattern
there seems to be a reward for that. We
are rewarded for what we do right and we
are given a sharp blow on the rear end
when we do wrong and out of this comes
integrity the final footing of things
upon the basis of the realities of life.
Now in the case of the the certain
fables that we can think of that are
repetitious take for example the legend
of Samson. This legend is found in at
least five different religions and over
a period of thousands of years.
The stories are almost always identical.
A version of all of the Samson stories
are found in various evidences such as
Hercules and other great heroes who made
the same mistakes, did the same things,
received the same punishments, and were
finally raised to some kind of higher
recognition.
The Odyssey of Homer appears again and
again in the literature of the world.
But it is not the incident that is
important or the story. It is the
unfoldment of a pattern of laws that
things are according to the realities of
a life bigger than ours. We live in a
universe which we talk about conquering
but which inevitably conquers us. We
break rules of nature and we suffer
accordingly. We break rules of ethics
and we destroy ourselves. We destroy
ourselves through extreme competition.
We destroy ourselves through ulterior
motives for lack of self-control, lack
of self-discipline, lack of integrity,
lack of faith, lack of love, lack of
hope. These things when they are
permitted to endure get us into trouble
and it becomes evidence that that nature
and nature's god wants us to keep these
rules and do these things according to
the highest moral ethics that we know.
Morality and ethics then more or less
arise from experience. They arise from
doing the same thing. The burglar robs
many houses and is not caught. But
finally he is. The individual who
commits a crime of importance may escape
the judgment of jury but in some way the
tragedy comes back to him. We are paid
for what we do in the coin of
recompense. If we do well, we get a good
record. If we do badly, we get a poor
record.
One of these, one of the most ex
important examples of this was the case
of Cryus, who in ancient times was the
richest man who ever lived. Of course,
he'd be more or less in the middle class
only today, but in those times he was
the top man in all matters of money. He
led a philosopher once into his great
treasuries, which were overwhelming and
overflowing with gold and jewels and
precious things. and his tremendous
amassment was the greatest in all the
world. And he showed it proudly of all
the wealth, all the power, all the
things he had treasured and gathered,
all the successes that were piled into
that great treasury. And the philosopher
looked at it for a moment and then he
turned to Cus and he said, "Yes, and a
man with better iron will take it all
away from you."
This is happening right now.
We have all these various attitudes of
success but weaponry can take away
almost anything that the individual can
accumulate himself included.
So all way back in those times it became
obvious to people that when you do
things consistently wrong where you do
not keep the rules of life
punishes. Not because it is despotic,
but because like a good parent, it is
determined to prove that only right can
survive. And until right survives,
everything that evades it or avoids it
fades away and is not seen again. And so
we come now to the little story about
the feast of Belshazza who is king of
all Calaldia.
And in this day story, a prophet by the
name of Daniel as found in the book of
Daniel reads the handwriting on the wall
of the banquet hall of Belshaza.
All the various uh wise people of Calia
tried to write to read or interpret
these letters which appeared as though
in blood upon the wall of the great
banquet hall where Belshazzer and his
cohorts were celebrating a victory over
their enemies. And finally, no one being
able to interpret it, they sent for
Daniel. And Daniel looked at the
inscription on the wall and gave it
according to various additions of the
scriptures about a dozen var
interpretations.
But the mind the main one the one that
has come down to us is the most
important as the one which says you are
found
lacking. You are weighed in the balance
and the balance doesn't balance. So that
in reality and substance you await in
the balance and found wanting.
Now I couldn't use that title but I kind
of tucked a couple of words on the end
of it that I'm afraid cannot be
attributed to pure Belshaza. It is I
added after it you weighed and in in the
balance and found wanting too much.
Every one of us today is suffering from
the fact that if we are weighed in the
balance, there are certain factors that
would require immediate correction. We
would be forced to change a number of
our ways and our thoughts and we would
find that we can support this by a
careful study of the scriptures of every
important religion of the world. And a
thousand years from now, our experience
will be part of a scripture written at a
later date. We are going to have exactly
the same interpretation and we are going
to have our problem attributed to deity.
We are going to be weighed in the
balance and we are going to be found
unbalanced, un untrue, unfair,
unfaithful and for that we will be
punished. Now, the ancients looking at
this situation and comparing it to 50
others that had gone before over a
period of 5,000 years, all coming out
exactly the same would assume that it is
not well for the individual to practice
those faults by which such predition
such conditions are produced.
If we are to be weighed in the balance
and found wanting, then we must
definitely
realize that we are talking about some
form of integrities or values. We know
that because like Belshazza, we're in
the midst of a war. We are being
conquered and conquering. We are trying
desperately to maintain a system of
beauty and truth by means of violence.
This is against practically every
religion and shows up time and time
again in the fables that are written
about the conduct of mankind. We are
therefore in the constantly in the
presence of evidence. And when someone
says what truth is there that you can't
do as you please. The truth is there is
the proof is in the fact that
individuals who do as they please have
two choices. If they choose to do what
is right, they are successful. And if
they choose to do what is wrong,
failure, as it is as inevitable as it
was 2,000 years ago. The time factor
does not overcome the qualities of
ethics. There only can be one surviving
world pattern, and that is a pattern in
which integrity is the foundation upon
which all else is built. The only nation
that is going to survive is a nation
that is honest. The only leader that
will ultimately lead anywhere and
accomplish any good is the leader who is
honest. And the only citizen who will
have a safe do in the world here or to
come will be the citizen who is honest.
All these subtitles, all this crime, all
this evasion is simply a kind of
madness. And nearly all powerful rulers
have suffered from this type of
insanity.
The type of believing in the
infallibility of their own will over the
inevitables of life.
Each each individual who comes to a
certain point of egotism decides that he
is greater than the laws that govern
man. He tries to break these laws and
assure his circumstance the laws break
him.
So we have now a problem that is coming
into focus that we are all being weighed
in the balance again.
And we are beginning to realize as not
for a long time have we been thinking
that we are really being tested for
something. We are being checked to find
out what we really believe. We are going
to be divided the wheat from the shaft.
We are going to be found guilty of wrong
or blessed for the rewards of right. And
these decisions have to come and there
is no way of avoiding them. So we look
at what there is. Now also we know from
the story of the Old Testament and many
other books, man was not merely a play
thing of the Lord. Man was made to
reflect and reveal the glory of re of
reality.
The actual work of man was to prepare
him for universal citizenship to prepare
him for an eternal existence in a
beautiful and eternal world.
Up to this time this has not happened.
But it's also true that up to this time
there is no world ever come that was
worth that deserved it. Many things
start beautifully and nobly. But of
course along the way temptation comes
in. Opportunity for profit comes in. The
desire for personal recognition comes
in. All these things. Little by little
the ethics disappears.
It disappears with corruption. And there
can be no corruption in nature that is
not subject to punishment. And the
stories of the cities of the plains and
Solomon Gamada are not fables. They have
occurred many many many times some
within the lifetime of the present
generation. Always however back of it is
the immutable fact that good must
prevail and that which is not good must
disappear and it cannot be thrown away
and it cannot be taken away by prayer.
If we believe that we can be reformed by
asking for reformation,
we find that it hasn't happened. The
only time that we can be reformed is
then we of our own will and intention
correct the faults that we suffer from
and present ourselves in our best light
to the law which judges all things. This
problem then we are facing in in the
present international situation. We have
discovered more than man ever knew
before and have used it more completely.
We have advanced further in science than
ever before and have fallen back deeper
in ethics than any civiliz civilization
of importance. Others have fallen as a
result of doing the thing we are doing.
But we somehow hope vainly that we will
succeed where truth tells us we have to
fail. Now having come to some kind of a
reasonable realization of this, we can
pass from the great picture which we all
see every day on television, read it in
the newspaper, see it set forth in the
journal and hear it shouted for the
pulpits of 10,000 Turkish that we have
got to do something to change the basic
pattern of society.
Now we find that society functions well
only when the leader is just and the
follower is honest. Until this
combination exists, there is no
permanence in anything. There is no way
of preventing a people from become
becoming disobedient if leadership is
disloyal or unworthy of leadership. It
is therefore necessary for us to start
somewhere to find out what we have to
do. And uh we we can get a great deal of
information on this subject from the ten
commandments and the sermon on the
mount. These two documents we regard as
theological.
We may like to think that they're just
something that somebody said but didn't
really mean or it was something that
somebody said but nobody can live up to
it. This is not true. There's nothing in
the ten commandments or the sermon on
the mount that is impossible.
But there is much in both of them that
is impossible if the indivi individual
himself wishes to remain impossible.
If we prefer to take a chance and use
the cocaine and die from an overdose 2
or 3 years later, we have the right to
do this. No one can stop us. But the
punishment comes directly upon
ourselves. Everyone who abuses any fact
of life will suffer from the abuse which
he has committed. There is no escaping
this, no way of escaping it. And so
because of its inevitability and
immutability, it has been attributed to
deity. It is attributed to the only
power or force or energy that we ne can
recognize which when it operates ar
gives righteous judgment, bestows upon
that which it works with the the
blessing of integrity and punishes that
which departs from the laws of life.
These uh realizations come back to all
of us. Now in this particular generation
there are a great many people who are
beginning to wake up to these things. In
the last 5 or 10 years the interest in
trying to find an answer. This this
interest has increased a thousandfold.
Hundreds of organizations have been
created in an effort to try to find an
answer that will stand up against the
pressures of the time.
Well, some of these organizations have
done very well uh for people and some
others have done very well for
themselves.
This problem is one we all have to face.
Wherever an improvement is demonstrated
or dynamically disseminated in the hope
of personal profit, there's something
wrong in the picture. The idea that
we're going to find the illusions, the
truths behind them for $100 an evening
is much much wrong. No, no can do. Not
possible. The first point about a true
ethics is to get out of the idea that
the reformation of mankind is the
greatest financial opportunity in the
history of the world.
that never was such a chance to get rich
out to trying to make people behave
themselves.
Unfortunately, however, the emphasis is
wrong to begin with and that people do
not behave themselves because the
inspiration of integrity is missing.
And therefore, in this t time it is very
important for us to realize that we are
combining not for profit but for
salvation.
that we are coming together not because
we can buy and sell cheaper from each
other or now we are not going to build a
new civilization to get over tariff
laws. These kind of things or we are not
going to think of anymore. We are going
to discover that we must unite for
common good or perish that we have been
given every opportunity imaginable to
improve our dispositions and we for the
most part stay the same. On the other
hand, the Lord works in mysterious ways.
Truly, we can go back to the scripture
again and we have the history of the
good people. We have those who kept the
law sometimes under great stress and
privation and even death. Martyrdom in
some instances was their only visible
reward. But these good people are
blessed in the life of the of the world
in which we live. And because of this
fact that this material world is not the
whole story, those who have lived well
even if it has cost them their lives are
richer than those who have had
everything in this world that they
wanted and die impoverished in ethics.
So we have to make some decisions in
this particular problem. The decisions
of how to handle the responsibilities of
the moment. Reforms are necessary in
every area. But wherever there is a
reform, it uh interferes with somebody's
profit
and it's got it's the p fi that's
worrying us. The other type of profit is
hard to find.
We are actually working constantly under
the shadow of ulterior motive.
We feel that this tremendous sorrow and
pain and worry of the world is a
tremendous opportunity
to forward other ulterior motives and
become very wealthy over the sufferings,
uncertainties and fears of our
neighbors.
This is only going to make it worse.
This is going to bring again another
example of what happens uh to those who
do not keep the rules. The older
scriptures tell us that they were cast
out, that they wandered in the desert
and had to go through great trials and
tribulations before they were permitted
to ask forgiveness and return to the
rules of the game. This is the the
proper attitude we have now. What do we
need primarily at the moment? We need
what we have needed probably off and on
for the last 6 7 8,000 years. Something
that we've had small examples of or
short periods in which integrities were
fashionable. But these were not very
common and didn't last very long. What
we have got to do now is to begin to
build in the values that we know to be
right and build them into an idealistic
system.
An I a materialist is essentially an an
atheist.
A material materialist does not believe
in a divine power or he wouldn't act the
way he does.
Now the fact that he does what he does
if he feels he is a free agent that he
can do anything he pleases to do and for
a certain time and under certain
conditions he's correct. If he wants to
waste a life he can do it. If he wants
to drink himself to death he can do it.
If he wants to go under narcotics he can
do it. and he will shorten his life or
fill his life with sorrows and miseries
and sickness and a premature death as a
reward for his disobedience of common
sense and nominal reasonable patterns.
But there is a way in which we can
gradually get over this primary
materialism
by really screaming the scriptures again
from which we learn that the earth and
the fullness thereof belong to the Lord.
This is something we've completely
forgotten as at the present time the
earth belongs to whoever can get a
mortgage on it
>> and everyone Napoleon, Caesar, Hitler,
Mussolini and all these have tried to
get that mortgage. The earth is here and
they are gone. Actually we do not own
this planet. We do not own anything
because all we have is a right of
occupancy.
And just as sure as we have this right
of occupancy, we can we can loan it to
somebody else. We can bestow it. But
whatever we bestow again is only the
right of occupancy. We have a world
built upon great
extravagances
of land of of our power of wealth of
profit. All of these things contributing
to the troubles we have. We cannot have
a world that is devoted to immorality
and at the same time have a beautiful
moral universe.
And we have to stop where we can. We
know that most of the important
corrections would result in somebody
else getting mad at us. We would be
interfering with a glorious system of
profit upon which our whole world way is
built. we would take away from the great
and powerful organizations their ability
to control the financial resources of
the planet. So to prevent this from
happening, anything is preferable.
Things must remain the same or else the
great pattern of economic wealth will be
disturbed. Well, it has failed already.
It is already failing again and more.
and in a little time is going to be such
a complete failure that nobody can
believe it anymore. But they will for a
little time string desperately and try
to perpetuate a system of profit which
has no foundation in facts.
I would imagine now that our 6 billion
fellow countrymen, our fellow world
citizens uh continue to multiply at the
present rate and we will find in a short
time that we will use up every natural
resource that we possess that we will
destroy practically every base uh
resource of our planet. Every day more
ponds and lakes and rivers are being
polluted.
Someday there just won't be any other.
But these people work on the basis that
when the time comes we will find
something to do with these things so
that we can keep on being just what we
are. This is unrealistic
because unless there is a terrible
catastrophe which destroys the greater
part of the earth's population which it
probably is not in hand because the case
is not clear enough but we will have to
face the importance of becoming moderate
people. Now I watch the newspapers
pretty closely and these people who are
working so hard to get hold of
everything they have do not seem to be
very happy with it.
These great patterns of wealth, these
fabulous incomes, these enormous
investments, these these process of
practically buying and selling nations
doesn't seem to be doing anybody any
good.
The we only end up with the worst debt
that we haven't had in history. And we
also make more enemies every day than
they've made than the Persians ever
knew. So we are not getting anywhere
with this at all. I think we should
begin it now to think firmly of
rewriting history, rewriting it for the
school child, rewriting for the grammar
school and a little large copy for the
high schools. And we also should make a
nice deluxe binding on some of them for
the parents to read because we need to
know exactly what is happening in our
world. We don't need to know just how
many dollars we made or whether we have
a desperate deficit this year or not. We
want to know exactly what is happening
to a world without conscience, without
integrity, and without moral
foundations.
We want to know what happens when we
ridicule the best things there are in
life, glorify that which is corrupt, and
become addicted to all kinds of crimes
and degeneracies.
This can be result in a another
cataclysm such as that which was written
on the wall of Belshazzer Palace. We are
we being weighed now and we will be
there's no need to go out and get
tremendously upset. It's the only
problem is that we do need to go out and
get upset to the degree that we are
willing to begin to work on ourselves.
Every family should have some kind of
moral instruction.
It should bestow this moral instruction
upon its children. Every business should
have a moral code by which that business
is controlled and which will not be
broken. Every profession should have a
moral ethical code for the practice of
the members of that profession which
will not be exploited, will not be
corrupted and will not lead to the
transformation of the motives of a
profession. The motive of medicine is to
help people who are sick. Today the
motive is cash.
The tremendous amount of money involved.
Money can lead and does lead and is a
form of moral compromise.
It is something that should never enter
into human relationships. It will
remain, however, as long as nobody
really minds.
We talk about it, but when the time
comes to act, we are too busy doing
something else. I think there should be
a legal code set up for all the major
professions
fixing completely and entirely the
method and means of administering that
profession. What it can do, what it
cannot do, what it can charge and what
it cannot charge and the penalties for
overcharging.
This is important. Actually, the the
laborer is worthy of his hire. The
doctor is worthy of a fee that is
appropriate to the service he renders,
but he is not entitled to exploit the
sick. All these things are part of the
laws of the moral code.
Now, the sacred books of the world, all
of them were moral codes. They were
codes that were intended to help se
people to understand what is good and
what is bad.
Nearly all of these books contain a
factor involving the fact that those who
keep these rules are blessed in the
sight of the universe. They are the ones
who are keeping the laws, keeping the
rules and are deserving of further
consideration.
Now in China in the old days they the
doctors had a cute rule. The patient
hired a family physician. This family
physician had his appointment on one
basis only. He was to keep the family
well. He received his monthly salary as
long as they were well. When they got
sick, his p pay stopped. The entire
motive now is obviously to get them well
again. Whereas with us today, the longer
there we are they're sick, the more
fortunate the physician becomes.
But uh these things have to be worked
through in some practical way. So we
need an world ethics, something that
gives us the strength and character to
begin a new world charter, a new world
parliament of faith and knowledge and
the seat and center of it must be
religious.
Now this religion doesn't mean that the
individual has to believe in any
particular appearance of deity because
nobody has seen any of them. But it
means that there must be an acceptance
of the fact that a divine moral
principle is at the root of life
demonstrated by the fact that every
trouble we have comes from disobeying
moral principles.
Therefore whether we believe in deity or
not if we believe in health and survival
we have to keep the rule. There is no
other way. So we go into other fields
where there's all kinds of
dissimilations to give us of problems
and sickness. We also need to have a
complete reconstruction of the basic
codes for higher education.
The France. Now the all of education is
based upon one basic idea to take a
field of specialized learning where
there is probability of advancement and
a very superior type of employment.
We are out to get the best job there is.
Well, this has been badly broken up,
however, by some modern discoveries. And
when these discoveries came along, there
were no graduates to uh take the jobs.
The discoveries were too recent. But
they'll come and we'll gradually have
various experts. And by the time the
expert gets the full training, this
machine will be obsolete.
This is the same way all the way along.
You're not supposed to do this. Life is
not supposed to be an addiction to a
profession that will get riches and
nothing else. There is no comfort, no
duty, no love or finness in working
machines. We may say yes, but they do
help people. Certainly they help people
but not to the degree of making them the
principal objective in life. The
principal objective in life when we want
to help people is to care for people, to
love people, to serve people, to be kind
to people and to advance those common
virtues by which the people as a whole
advance in their understanding of life,
in the care of their children and in the
preparation of their own futures. The
final purpose of the civilization is
that the human being shall improve that
he shall become sufficient to be wiser
and more virtuous and a better human
being and a better person. He is not
here simply to leave a fortune to his
descendants in his will.
And uh very often he doesn't get that
far. They break it up and take it away
from him while he's still alive.
And this of course is considered to be
pretty good business.
It may be good business but it is bad
life and we are all doing good business
by doing wrong
and this is not good
and uh we can't expect everyone to
change their ways but we can take a
little forth suitable stand in these
things. Each individual is the master of
a small world of his own which is a
miniature of the great world.
And this miniature world of his own he
calls his family and it is surrounded by
various friends, neighbors and so forth
and is a little constellation in itself.
This little world is within the control
of various members of this family.
There is a perfect possibility of this
family becoming a better family. This is
the very secret and idea behind the
teachings of Menus the great Chinese
philosopher. The Menus believed that the
archetype of universal peace is a family
living in harmony.
where relatives and friends and
neighbors cannot get along together. We
have no right to expect nations to
become better because nations are not
enough not problem. Is it true? But they
are actually aggregates of individual
disorders. And as long as the individual
is disordered in his own living, there
will be no solution merely by spreading
this disorder over the world. There is
no solution in treaties in great packs
because before the things are even
signed we begin to find the ulterior
motives that dominated their
preparation. Everything has something
behind it that is not right. And uh as
long as that happens we're going to have
more examples of Belshazza's feast. What
we're looking for now is something that
has right behind it rather than right on
the surface an ulterior motive
underneath.
And this is true in the affairs of
nations in every line of business. It is
true in the quality of goods and it is
very true in entertainment.
Gradually we see entertainment gradually
deteriorating with only one
consideration profit. And because of the
way in which the modern civilization is
centered, profit centered around
ignorance and stupidity.
The the less intelligence this art is,
the greater its appeal. Nobody cares
about these things. And no one has
developed the judgments to judge them.
There's no reason why a very short time
common sense could not make a major
change in human attitudes.
But until that time comes, we've got to
do it ourselves. We've got to begin to
straighten out the various ideas behind
ourselves. And we also have to get a
clearer view of the what religion does
for mankind. We've got to be very
careful now when we learn that some many
religious groups are in bad trouble
economically. They have gotten
themselves into something that they
should never have been in. They have
forgotten
that the Lord God does not live in a
palace.
We build great churches as Ingisol said
cathedrals are for saints, dungeons for
sinners. and the dungeons are in the
foundations of the cathedrals.
What we need is to realize that then
finally the most perfect church of all
is the human heart. For it is here that
the individual at least scient sent
sentimentally comes into contact with
the realities of himself. We need to
recognize religion not as a new source
of wealth but as a new source of
strength against the corruptions of
wealth.
We do not need more stained glass
windows and nor more uh mighty
cathedrals. What we need is the simple
place of worship. Our forefathers had
this a little wooden church with a
pastor who made only a few dollars a
month with a small flock of devout
people who worked in the ground with
their
harvest and came to church on Sunday in
the family wagon. This type of thing had
something about it that was good. We can
say it was stupid and old-fashioned and
all that, but it was sincere.
And and the little church that is
sincere has much to commend it, while
the great church that is not sincere has
nothing to recommend it whatsoever. So
all the way along the line, we've got to
gradually do that which will prevent us
from being found wanting.
And the reason why we will be found
wanting is because we want too much. We
want everything.
We want to find new ways every day for
taking money away from somebody else. We
want some kind of a pretext to take
another vast amount of money for some
purpose that is of no permanent value.
While all things are judged by money, a
religion is going to uh be very dire
trouble. When they showed uh the Roman
coin to Jesus and asked him what they
should do in matter of taxes, Jesus
replied, "Render unto Caesar that which
is Caesars's, but unto God that which is
his." And this is exactly our problem.
There's a great deal of difference. We
cannot render unto God the things that
belong to Caesar.
And we cannot pay for our sins whether
it's coinage that belongs to Caesar. We
can pay keep out of jail maybe by paying
our fines with that money but we do not
increase in stature or in dignity or in
magnitude of insights. So we have to
recognize that there is religion
desperately needed today and desperately
divided.
Here we have a religious world which
includes according to a very late
statement that I saw approximately 3 and
3/4 billion human beings.
The other part of the population isn't
made up of of atheists but very largely
of primitive peoples about which we have
very little knowledge. But the majority
of human beings believe in good.
And because 3/4 of the earth's
population believes in something good,
why do we have 3/4 of the earth's
population either in arms or in the
armament industry?
Why do we have these things?
Why is it that somewhere along the line
we've lost
kindness, lost friendship,
lost love for each other, and have all
kinds of strange ulterior motives that
pass for integrities but have no
foundation in them.
So, we wait in the balance and the
people are beginning to see some funny
writing on the wall and they're not
quite sure what it is, but there's
always a possibility that a new message
is being put there. There are words and
teachings and ideas about the future.
Some are very beautiful, some are
fearful, and very few are really
essentially materialistic today. Even
our most hardened materialists are
beginning to look for an excuse to
become idealists
and they can find it if they want it.
But the point is that we are all
beginning to worry worry seriously about
the depletion of our resources about the
population of explosions
about the diseases and natural disasters
which correspond neatly to the plagues
of Egypt. And we find that all these
things have been repeated time and time
again. The the sands of the desert have
buried more civilizations than we'll
ever know. And with unless we want to be
part of that which is wiped out by our
own stupidity and stupidity, we've going
to have to change our ways. We're going
to have to begin to live the things we
claim to believe. We're all trying to do
something about it. We all are reading
better books. We were all talking about
these things. Most people who are
interested in our activities here have
been trying to live these points and
principles and are trying still to be
better people. And this is this is the
solution. Only by becoming better people
can we have a better world. Only by
curing these selfish instincts which
have dominated us for ages can we really
have the kind of life that we all need.
Belshaza was quite king in his day and
he loved to exploit and enslave people.
He became a potential ruler of the
world. He had joined in with a number of
others like Genjis Khan and some of the
early Caesars and the Greek conquerors
that went out to conquer the whole
world.
He was the Roman Empire was the first
great socialistic
uh democracy or oligarchy whatever you
want to call it. Rome became mistress of
the world. Her colonies were everywhere.
She owned half the globe and what other
she didn't own she was working on.
But in the sum of it all, Rome died and
miserably ended because of the decay of
the government.
Little by little, all these imprisoned
peoples began to break away and Rome no
longer had the physical strength to hold
them. Now, if this holding had not been
a physical policing,
Rome might have lived another 2 or 3,000
years. But she could not police the
territories she had conquered. She
should never have conquered in a way
that required policing. It was not that
these colonies should be controlled by
force or by military means. They should
have been controlled by friendship
because these people should have be
grateful for what Rome had done for them
and not panicky over what Rome was doing
to them. There was no reason why a
conquering power should be destroyed. If
that conquest is carried on in a spirit
of sharing good,
if the conquest was bringing teachers
and idealists and inventors and artists
and musicians into common understanding,
if crops and and produce of all kinds
was better, these things would be
excused and the people would live
together in happiness. But where
conquest is simply putting a death spot
over another country or putting a half a
dozen of your death spots in different
countries. All this is part of rule and
ruin which is one of the problems we say
so deeply. And of course from the time
of Belshazzer on down the same problems
have continued.
And the Bible incident is perfectly
justified in saying that there is some
kind of a moral factor, a mystical
factor involved. Now according to the
Bible, of course, this mystical factor
is deity that some way this is all due
to the fact that deity weighs them in
balance and found them wanting. But the
deity that found them wanting is still
here.
Now if there was no deity that was found
the morning and they simply were
outwitted by two other nations or became
jealous of them then we are still in the
same picture because today we are in the
midst of a world that's jealous of us.
We are in a world that would take over
most of each other's countries at the
slightest provocation
if if any. We are in a world in which
out of all the progress we have made
could sometime become the greatest
holocaust of all time, nuclear war.
Though nothing stands between us and
this disaster except ethics and ethics
is a is our way of expressing divine
will. There is only the will of deity
between us and that difficulty.
Now if we trust to the Lord or if we
trust to the laws of nature, if we trust
to the universal plan as we have seen it
from the beginning of time, we are
comparatively safe. But if we break the
tradition that has been established by
the ages, if we break the rules, then
come to the same end with all other rule
breakers, it's our own fault. We are too
big now, too grown up now to play
warfare in sandboxes.
We are no longer children throwing mud
pies at each other. We are powerful
individuals who have no real
understanding of the basic unity of
life. They were in the same type of
situation uh that we find for instance
in Japan at one time when the Japan was
first open to the west. We sent a
council general over there to act as an
ambassador.
The first thing that he wanted when he
got there was beef steaks.
And at that time, most of Japan was
vegetarian.
In fact, the government was subsidizing
vegetarianism.
So, everyone who had an animal of any
kind rep drove it into the forest and
hid it.
And they had an awful time until they
finally caught an old steer and finally
got the stakes for the American
ambassador.
And now on the site where this thing
occurred is a beautiful monument topped
by a statue of the bull who died to give
an American ambassador his favorite
meat.
Now this is sort of a ridiculous
situation but it shows the tendency that
we have. What we want we want. What we
had we're going to have. And this going
on and on and on in spite of the daily
warnings of our troubles. So if anybody
has a real idea of doing something
worthwhile, it might be good for them to
sit down quietly and make a chart or
plan of their own lives. Why are they
alive? What are they doing? What is
going to happen to what they have? Who
is going to use it better than they
have? Why are we going to leave this to
that and that to this? What is behind
all this? We have more a few more years
of life. What are we going to do with
them? Are we going to keep right on
wasting them? Are we going to live so
that the doctor's bills eat up most of
our estate?
Are we going to get tangle into troubles
with other people until the lawyers eat
up the rest of the estate? Are we going
to live this way or are we going to
gradually begin to put the world in
order? Put it into a pattern of
realities. put it into a pattern of
facts and values with which we can live.
The idea that we want too much seems to
be universal
and money becomes the only answer to
that. Well, it's all right if people
want what they can get, I guess, but
they shouldn't want what is
unreasonable.
They get nothing out of it. I have read
recently several accounts of some of our
very wealthy theatrical people. When I
mean wealthy, I mean that who have
fortunes up into the hundreds of
millions.
Not one of these people is happy. Not
one of them has many real friends. Not
one of them knows what to do with the
money.
And uh most of it will probably
ultimately be doled out as alimonies.
Nobody seems to know what they're going
to do with this great wealth. They can
only sleep in one bed. They can only
live in one house. So, they get a summer
house, a yacht, and a winter house and
loan it to their friends cuz they never
go there. Or they go up to Las Vegas and
be relieved of some of their spare cash.
These are the things that people
struggle and die for to get that bank
account and they don't know what to do
with it after they get it. It doesn't do
them anything in the term of happiness.
They're just as miserable as the poor.
In fact, more miserable. And many of
them are sitting up all night with their
lawyers trying to figure out how to
balance their taxes.
And so, this is the desirable thing.
This is the thing that lifts people
above all competition in life. The
simple life is still the best. the
simple life of the individual who has
what he needs, a reasonable amount of
luxury, but not enough wealth to destroy
the next three generations of his own
family.
If he has too much money, his children
will suffer. And if that goes on, their
children will suffer. And wealth is the
root of indolence and waste. And this
planet is too much now depleted by waste
to continue indefinitely in this way. So
religion, it seems to me, should include
not only a love of God and a love of our
fellow man, but a determination to
protect our world from corruption as far
as we can do so. to prevent waste, to
prevent the misuse of natural resources,
and to put the conservation of resources
and energies as a primary part of our
faith, not as something that has to be
worked out by our politicians in
Washington or in some state capital.
Religion should mean that a world in
which we are enriching values
of a really religious people will always
be a people protecting the sacred things
of life, protecting love and friendship
and faith and kindness and compassion.
These are the things that enrich life.
The other things material and otherwise
really in the end impoverish life.
We we need to have the closeness that
comes from a simple sympathy for each
other. A kind of relationship by which
we will not in any way that we can
prevent injure any other person. So that
uh we can we can begin to live with some
of these things and by living this way
we will fulfill part of this Bible story
that we are so much concerned with. The
the siege of Troy
is a story of the of a two-fold world
locked in conquest
over a vanity.
The great wars of the ancients were
fought for power and glory and wealth.
The great wars of the middle ages were
fought for physical power or clerical
power. The great crusades
were the same thing we see coming back
today in the problem of Islam and
Christianity.
Back in the crusades, the Christians
lost the war. They could not regain the
Jerusalem which remained in the hands of
the infidel. But when it was all over
and the crusade ceased, the infidel
voluntarily opened the roads of
pilgrimage so that the followers of
Christians could visit the holy city in
perfect safety whenever they wanted to.
But they weren't going to have it taken
away from them by force.
Sulleon the magnificent and as a master
it is said uh Rabbi my monities one of
the greatest of the Jewish scholars. So
little by little uh we are going to have
to take care of this. We have two
militant creeds now and Muslimism and
Christianity are dangerous loggerheads.
The faiths are more or less quiet but
are still very very strong. Small groups
like the six are beginning to give great
trouble everywhere. The problem of
religion is taking on a militant
atmosphere.
And this we do not want. This should be
stopped immediately. But it will never
stop as long as we call anyone who
disagrees with us in theology a heathen.
This is something that we have no right
to do because we have no right to to
believe that the individual with the
right heart and the right mind cannot
just see as far into the truth of things
as the members of our own denominations.
It is all a matter of beginning to
realize that if we don't live together,
we're going to leave a barren world
perhaps to the animals or the insects.
We don't know. But we cannot keep it
going this way. And religions still
aren't on speaking terms with each
other. Each one is has its own
infallibility.
And we have a hundred new sex that have
arisen in the last 10 years. Each of
which is the only one that is perfect.
So all these things gather again, the
same things taking on new clothes with
the same ideas in every case going on
and on and on. This we've got to get out
of our systems. If we can't change other
people, at least we can begin to temper
our own attitudes on these things. And
if even a small fragment of society
really changes its way of life, that
change can be developed into a world
movement.
The very tools that we want to get rid
of can be used to help us to get rid of
them
because we can prove conclusively to
anyone's commit that that a good piece
of merchandise at a proper price is
better for all concerns than a poor
piece at a high price. We have accepted
the high price because it's part of a
great competitive era. But gradually we
are waking up to the fact that
competition is nothing but generalized
selfishness.
It is not a virtue and the pro the
proceeds of it have no blessing before
man or deity.
So all these things come up and they
work. But it's nice to realize how the
Bible has anticipated them and then
given this power that makes things work
into a pattern makes this power God.
The God that wrote the in living fire
the tablets of the law on the crest of
Si.
This deity was not visible to Moses.
But Moses is supposed to have been a
lawgiver and he seems to have been wise
in the wisdom of the Egyptians and other
strange people of the past.
Whatever it is, he touched the the
Phoenician and the Calaldian and the
Babylonian and the Assyrian foundations
of knowledge.
Then someone said, "Well, what was this
handwriting on the wall?"
And nobody could read it.
Well, there was a man by the name of
Garrett who was the astronomer pardon me
Gaper who was the astronomer of Cardinal
Rishelu
and he wrote a little book called
unheard of curiosities
and he had an answer for that question
which might not be the only one. It
might not be the real one but it is
certainly an interesting one. He says
that the whole concept was based on the
Hebrew alphabet.
In other words, the constellations
are the consonants constellations in the
heavens are the consonants or Hebrew
consonant letters. The planets are the
vowels which move constantly through the
patterns of the constellations. And in
every move they make they spell out
words because in every word there must
be a vowel. And in many cases in the
Hebrew the vowels are not written. But
in any event the motion of these vowels
through the star groups with each of the
consonants a letter to results in an
endless pattern of words. And these
words if they can be understood or
analyzed or explained might tell us the
whole story. For instance, if you have
two constellations that one is a B and
one is a T, then the vowel move vowels
move through it. If you put a A moves
through it, it becomes bat.
If a wager thought comes through it, it
becomes a bit
and so on. All of the forms of the
letters and if something else is very
small, it becomes a bit.
All these letters moving through the
constellations create an an immense con
sequence of word poems. And if we could
read those word poems with the
constellations and the planets in them,
we might have the secret of a celestial
language that has been in use since the
beginning of time. It might be in some
respect similar to our astrological
speculations, but it is not prophetic
necessarily. It simply tells, if we know
how to read it, that there is a constant
communication of energies between the
invisible world of causes and the
visible world of effects. It's a very
stimulating and interesting idea and I
think sometime someone will do something
with it. We have Gerald's book, by the
way, if anyone is interested. which is
in our library collection. But in all
cases, we're looking for an answer.
We're looking for some way to solve this
problem. We see the handwriting coming
in a thousand different ways,
particularly in red letters in our own
hearts. We know something is wrong. We
know that the world that we're bringing
our children into is not the world that
we want them to be in. And we know that
they do not know a better world because
we've never been able to convince them
of it. But if we could prove to instance
to members of any major faith that their
own stories, the fables and legends and
myths of religion are all of them
explanations of universal laws in their
various aspects. And that these stories
therefore all tell of what God is doing
to certain things under certain
circumstances and conditions. And with
that realization to work from, it seems
as though we ought to be able to solve
some of these problems.
Actually, the beginning of it all is not
that we should dash off and try to join
some religion. The thing is that we
should grow up with our reading,
writing, arithmetic all cooperating to
help us to become better people and not
just simply smarter people. And there
should be reading, writing, original,
arithmetic and ethics.
There should be an idealism in every
heart in the world. A dream of something
better. A dream that can be fulfilled to
some degree by anyone who wants to may
give the time and effort to it. But a
life should be a span of years in which
at least a part is dedicated to the
service of the eternal plan upon which
we all depend for existence and without
which the world itself falls into chaos.
And uh with now that so many people are
becoming interested in these things, it
is very important that we judge these
people and these organizations
thoughtfully and always remembering that
the real sincere uh group of people or
individuals are the ones who give all
and demand the least. that they want
more and more of people to love each
other, serve each other, protect each
other. They are not in business. They
are in idealism,
philosophy, ethics,
morality and all the things that help to
make a better world. And if we can find
groups of this kind uh which have within
them a reasonable degree of integrities
and a reasonable degree of dedication,
we can help them all to do better work
and we can do better ourselves. Because
when we work for something bigger than
we are, that is the time when we have a
right to feel a little bit bigger
ourselves. But while we are not doing
things to help, we are without knowing
or realizing doing things to hinder. And
this is no time for hindrance. This is a
time for all individuals to renew their
dedications
to the principles of reality and
integrity.
It is only through a quiet consistent
service of each other that we can prove
conclusively that religion is in our
hearts and in our daily lives. And
wherever anyone has a religious life
that is dedicated, they may have
troubles. Their religious life that is
honorable is not particularly popular or
too widespread. It is not appreciated
because it interferes with corruption
and nearly every good person has had to
fight corruption. But it is a great
fight. It is a worthwhile fight and the
individual who wins is already on his
way to a better state of existence. So
we do all we can but let's remember that
these stories in these scriptures about
all the wonders that God does. Job and
his comforters and uh all the Samson and
Delilah and the Song of Solomon and all
of these stories, fables and legends are
based upon centuries of experience with
principles that are immutable
that while the story may be fashioned
any time, maybe as late as tomorrow it
will come, but the fact behind the
story, the symbol is the concealing part
of a great moral truth. And the moral
truth is that the final end of all
things for the constructive value of
mankind is that all human beings will
unite in the love of the divine
principle and in the service and
affection for each other. This is what
we have to have if we're going to solve
the issues of the day. And I think now
we better bring it to a close this
morning.